[Music]
during the covet 19 pandemic the death
rate for african americans was as much
as six times higher than white america
the higher black pandemic deaths placed
a harsh spotlight on their long-standing
higher mortality and diminished
longevity in general unfortunately
diminished african-american life
expectancy predates the covet 19
pandemic by decades
the black white death gap for women is
about three years and for men closer to
five years the coveted 19 death
disparities may have to do with limited
access to healthy food in predominantly
black communities the housing density
the
need to work or else the inability to
practice social distancing but also
the underlying burden
of ill health
increased covet 19 mortality and
complications occur more often in
individuals with pre-existing conditions
like hypertension obesity diabetes and
cardiovascular disease comorbidities
that are more prevalent in african
americans
more high blood pressure more diabetes
more strokes
and more likely to die at early ages
from all causes put together
the question
is why why do black americans live
sicker and die younger than their white
counterparts
well one big factor is socioeconomic
status in the united states race is
closely tied to class with african
americans about twice as likely to be
living in poverty
on average education levels are lower as
well however even among african
americans whose socioeconomic status is
comparable to that of whites
despite the higher education and more
socioeconomic resources health outcomes
are
still
poorer
part of that has to do with lifestyle
behaviors for example fewer than five
percent of african american adults met
physical activity guidelines
smoking rates are actually comparable
though african-americans tend to be
exposed to more secondhand smoke and
have lower quit rates
this may be because they're more likely
to use menthol cigarettes which enhance
the addictive potential of nicotine
why menthols
because tobacco companies target the
marketing of mentholated products to
african americans
black lives
black lungs
similarly if you look at food messages
on african-american television shows not
only does black prime time contain a
greater number of food commercials
african-american audiences may be
receiving nearly three times as many
advertisements for low nutrient junk
such as candy and soda
that may be one reason why african
americans tend to consume
fewer fresh fruits and vegetables and
are more likely to eat junkier foods
of course where are you gonna get those
fresh fruits and vegetables there are
fewer supermarkets located in black
neighborhoods compared with white
neighborhoods as in four times fewer
supermarkets
what black neighborhoods do excel in
though
is
fast food
predominantly black neighborhoods have
60 percent more fast food restaurants
per square mile compared to
predominantly white neighborhoods
now of course dietary behaviors alone do
not fully explain the significant
differences in diet-related disease
patterns between racial groups there are
differences in employment and poverty
and home ownership and health care
access all of which can affect outcomes
but while there are certainly many
social and economic factors such as
racism and income inequality that
contribute to health disparities
there is good evidence that simply
eating a more plant-based diet could
help eliminate disparities in
cardiovascular disease and diabetes
here's the diabetes data even after
controlling for education income
physical activity and even bmi
non-blacks eating strictly plant-based
diets had 57 percent lower odds of
diabetes and among black vegans it was
even more striking
70 lower odds
and that was after taking bmi into
account so even at the same weight black
vegans had 70 lower odds of diabetes
than black omnivores
and the
racial disparity is only about half that
36 percent so the increased risk of
diabetes among black participants was on
the order of one
third while the protection afforded by
vegan diets in this subgroup was about
even just a vegetarian diet that
includes still eating dairy and eggs may
more than counteract the racial
disparity in diabetes risk
and they're not the same weight african
americans have higher obesity rates
cutting their lifespans by six years but
black vegetarians and vegans have less
than half the risk of obesity compared
to those who eat meat and this is after
adjusting for differences in physical
activity so even at the same exercise
levels those eating more plant-based had
but a fraction of the obesity risk
high blood pressure
in african americans hypertension is the
most significant contributor to their
increased cardiovascular disease burden
and mortality but
black vegetarians and vegans combined
had 44 lower odds of hypertension an
important finding for black individuals
where hypertension is so prevalent with
no benefit found for those who cut out
all other meat but continued to eat fish
and the same thing found for total
cholesterol and ldl cholesterol cutting
odds in half among black vegetarians and
vegans
as with non-blacks the researchers
conclude these results suggest that
there are sizable advantages to a
vegetarian diet in black individuals
what about
vegetarians versus vegans
the title gives it all away
cardiovascular disease risk factors are
even lower in african-american
vegans
this is something we've known about when
caucasian vegans have been compared to
vegetarians however it was not known
whether african american vegans exhibit
a more favorable cholesterol profile uh
until
now significantly lower ldl cholesterol
in vegans now of course the vegans were
also significantly slimmer on average
normal weight as opposed to the
overweight vegetarians but even after
taking that into account those eating
more plant-based had significantly lower
cholesterol
so there's a tremendous potential for
plant-based diets to promote health
among blacks living in the united states
in fact they may have an even greater
benefit for example african americans
have an excess burden of chronic kidney
disease not only because they have more
high blood pressure and diabetes but
there are genetic factors
eight percent to 12
of african americans are carriers of the
sickle cell trait which places them at
significantly higher risk of kidney
disease so while blacks represent
relatively small fraction of the u.s
population they account for more than a
third of all patients on dialysis due to
chronic kidney disease
and that's where plant-based diets can
come in shown to protect against both
chronic kidney disease development
as well
as progression
three-quarters of blacks are lactose
intolerant too
so would again stand to benefit even
more
from eating plant-based
it is unacceptable
that for decades the american health
care system has failed african americans
and other minority communities in terms
of helping to prevent some of our
leading killers
but that just makes it all the more
important for them to take the reins of
their own health destiny
[Music]
you